开火
Fire!
- 装填弹药 - 准备就绪
- Reload. - Stand ready!
上帝啊 你终于回来了
Good God, man!
你可寻到可食之物
Did you not find anything to eat?
大人 我一无所获
There's nothing to find, my Lord.
整个国家 方圆数英里
The whole countryside for miles and miles is stripped.
猪兔牛羊已绝迹 无任何可食之物
of every sheep, cow, pig, hare… of anything edible.
曾有法国农夫求见我们 以上帝之名
We had French peasants come up to us, crying piteously.
凄惨哀哭 乞求施舍给他们一片面包
in God's name for a piece of bread to keep alive.
挽救他们饥肠辘辘的孩子
their little ones who are dying for want of food.
他们孩子的死活与我而言无关痛痒
It's not their little ones I worry about.
我只关心我士兵的死活
It's my own soldiers.
法国人不会如往昔一样
It's a pity the French will not come out.
杀出来与我们一决胜负 这着实遗憾
and break lances with us, as they used to do.
若两军交锋 而我则能化身第一骑士兰斯洛
Then I could truly fancy I was Lancelot Du Lac.
而不是在这里坐以待毙
Instead of sitting here in our own shit.
徒为饿殍
and starving to death!
那些试图逃跑的混蛋算是解脱了
Except for the bastards who try and run away!
前进
Forward!
装弹药
Reload!
快跑 快跑
Run! Run!
停 停 等等
Stop! Stop! Wait!
别动
Don't move.
来吧 继续工作
Dai! Tornianno a lavorare.
伙计们 我们无暇胆颤
We do not have time to be afraid, my friends.
走 回去工作
Go, back to work.
你知道我们挖到哪儿了吗
Ah! Do you know where we are?
离城堡还有300英尺之遥
The castle's still 300 feet away.
上帝啊
Christ!
- 有多少人死于血痢 - 截至目前吗
- How many men have died of the flux? - So far?
两千人 并且另有三千人身染此病
Two thousand. And a further three thousand are sick with it.
不宜出战
and not fit to fight.
疫病在将我们有限的资源消耗殆尽
The sick are using up our limited resources.
陛下 以微臣之见
In my opinion, your Majesty,
应将病员与井分隔
they should be separated from the well.
并把他们送回英格兰
and transported back to England.
这将意味着我得从封锁线
That would mean that I would have to.
撤下数艘船只
take several ships from my blockade!
这血痢使我们痛失锐气一蹶不振 病源为何
What is the cause of this bloody flux that so unmans us?
陛下 关于病源 众说纷纭 莫衷一是
Your Majesty, there is much disagreement as to causes.
有人说疫病起于缺少供给
Some say it is the result of lack of supplies.
而还有人的观点恰恰相反
Others, by contrast,
称疫病肆虐是因贪致祸
say it comes of greed,
士兵们刚刚抵达之时饥不择食
the men having gorged themselves on unripe fruit.
胡乱以生水果和贝类充饥
and shellfish when they first arrived.
能肯定的是 人类迄今
What is certain is that there is no way known to man.
对此疫病的蔓延一筹莫展
to stop its spreading infection.
如果继续围攻
If the siege should continue for much longer,
恐怕陛下军中的一大部分士兵
I'm afraid a great portion of your Majesty's army will soon.
将很快埋骨布洛涅
be dug into the fields of Boulogne.
休再对我口出此言
I will not hear anymore about it!
你跟那些法兰西人一样可恶
You are as much my enemy as the French,
处处长他人志气
since you seek to demoralize, to lie about our weaknesses,
灭自己威风
and to spin tales of sickness.
那些人并非身染瘟疫 而是为胆怯所吓
These men are not sick from the flux but from cowardice!
我决不会让那些懦夫如愿返乡
And I will not send cowards home!
他们要么战死 要么被我悬尸路旁
They will either fight or I will hang them by the wayside.
你 让他们滚下病床
You! Get them from their sickbeds.
回到战壕里去 否则我要你项上人头
back into that trench, or I will make you a head shorter.
遵命 陛下
Yes, your Majesty.
还有 以后要对我据实以报
And in the future… tell me the truth!
也许按照名字的首字母顺序…
Perhaps the initials of these names…
陛下 加德纳主教求见
Majesty, Bishop Gardiner asks for an audience.
让他进来
Send him in.
陛下 吾等告退 走吧 女士们
Majesty. Come, ladies.
主教大人
Your Grace.
陛下
Your Majesty.
敢问关于陛下及其战事
I have come to hear if there is any fresh news of the King.
可有新消息传来
and his affairs?
陛下一切安好 状态极佳
The King is very well and in the best of spirits.
我听说他身心俱愉
I am told he has never seemed happier.
我们都将为陛下的健康及成功而祷告
We all pray for the King's life and his success.
陛下 既然现在您代陛下执掌朝纲
There is one matter I should discuss with your Majesty,
那臣有一事与您相商
since you act as Regent in his absence.
但说无妨
Go on.
我等近来在陛下身边的乐师中
Having discovered a nest of heretics.
抄剿了一个异教徒的老巢
among the King's musicians… and destroyed it…
我们发现甚至在陛下的王室中
We now discover that there are heretics.
也有异教徒潜伏
even in the King's privy chambers.
大人 您所指何人
Of whom do you speak, my Lord?
陛下的理发师及御厨
The King's barber and the royal cook.
我们已掌握了足够的证据
We have enough evidence.
起草控书
to draw up this draft indictment.
只需陛下签字即可
All that we require is your signature.
大人 我为您的兢兢业业而叹服
My Lord, I praise you for your diligence in these matters.
但我认为 要拘捕陛下如此亲信之人
But I do not think it proper to arrest men.
理当先问过陛下才是
so close to the King's person…without first asking him.
对了 还有一事
Oh, and there is one other matter.
听说温莎地区附近瘟疫肆虐
We have heard rumors of an outbreak of plague near Windsor.
我想把爱德华王子召入宫中
So I have decided to invite the Prince Edward.
与我同住
to come here to court and stay with me.
如您所愿 陛下
As you wish, Madam.
父亲
Pere!
- 父亲 - 宝贝 我的宝贝女儿
- Papa! - Chere! Mon cherie.
您没事吧
Comment vas tu?
- 没事 我很好 - 小姐
- Je vais bien. Tres bien. - Mademoiselle,
只要你肯合作
in return for your cooperation,
我就放你父亲走
I have decided to allow your father to escape.
合作
My cooperation?
你必须保证不会试着逃跑
You must promise not to try and escape yourself.
[拉丁语]他要放您走
Quiere dejarte ir.
但我得保证留下来
Pero tengo que prometer quedarme.
我女儿不走 我也不走
No me iré sin mi hija.
绝不
Nunca.
要不放了她 抓我吧
Deja que me atrape.
我再说一次 先生 我绝不走
Repito, señor, nunca me iré.
父亲 如他所说 我们别无选择
Papá dijo que no teníamos elección.
- 不行 - 父亲 听我说 能走一个算一个
- No puedo. - Mi padre me escuchó decir que podía caminar uno por uno.
我父亲同意了
My father agrees.
谢谢
Thank you.
他必须马上动身了
He must go now.
[拉丁语]保重
Cuidate mucho.
不要担心我
No te preocupes por mí.
你会没事的
Estarás bien.
我会想念您的
I'll miss you.
我相信你是个可敬的敌人
Creo que eres un enemigo honorable.
希望你能对我的宝贝女儿以礼相待
Espero que trates a mi querida hija con cortesía.
我向您保证
Le aseguro.
带他出去 放了他
Relee him outside the camp.
你还好吗 哈里
So, how are things, Harry?
还好
Good.
给 这儿有些吃的
Here. Here's some food.
- 那是你的口粮 - 你比我更需要它
- That's your food. - You need it more than I do.
我只是终日坐着打发时间而已
I just sit outside and watch the seagulls.
快 拿着
Go on, take it!
吃吧 哈里
Eat it, Harry.
还有那些宝马良驹 简直妙不可言
And the horses! The horse is magnificent.
非常欢迎你来 赫福德大人
I bid you most welcome, my Lord Hertford.
你能来此 说明你对王后执掌朝政
I take it your visit here confirms your confidence.
- 非常放心 - 是的 陛下
- in the Queen's Regency! - Majesty.
关于凯瑟琳王后的执政能力
Majesty, I have heard nothing but praise.
臣所耳闻
in all quarters for the dedication.
皆为褒奖
and skill of Queen Catherine in matters of state.
她头脑清醒 睿智过人
She has great clarity of mind,
男人好鲁莽行事 气愤抱怨
and a woman's touch which soothes and cures.
王后的韧性恰好能弥补这一点
where a man would usually rush into anger and complaint.
王子还好吗
And the boy?
爱德华王子喜乐安康
Prince Edward is well and healthy.
- 为王子的健康干杯 - 为王子干杯
- A toast to his health! - To the Prince.
- 为爱德华王子干杯 - 为王子干杯
- To Prince Edward. - To the Prince.
快说啊
Bring it round!
何事
What is it?
不得不禀报陛下
I have to tell your Majesty.
我收到消息 皇帝已拿下
that I have received word that the Emperor has seized.
其所攻打的要塞
both the fortresses he was besieging,
并且俘获1500名敌军
and has taken fifteen hundred enemy prisoners.
特雷维索 我早说过了
What did I tell you, Senor Treviso?
我认定你的计策会失败
I never trusted your methods.
- 一切都拖得太久了 - 陛下
- Everything has taken too long. - Majesty…
你不懂得如何带兵
And you don't know how to handle the soldiers!
没人在行
None of you do!
我发誓 该早点让你明白
I swear to God I could have told you.
包围战令大军孤立无援 百无聊赖
Siege warfare makes men idle and bored.
委顿不堪 我说的对吗 公爵
They get soft. Isn't that right, your Grace?
- 军队战斗力下降 - 的确如此
- The men get soft. - It's true,
军营里到处充斥着妓女
the camp is swarming with prostitutes.
但即便如此 考虑到当地情况
But even so, considering the conditions…
若遭遇突袭 我要确保大军
I want to make sure of the troops' good behaviour.
能够英勇作战
in case of an assault.
我们应提前引爆城墙下的一处炸药
We shall explode one of the charges under the castle walls.
出其不意
prematurely…without warning.
如此我们便可在危急之时
That way, we can observe the temper.
察知大军性情及应变能力
and the disposition of the troops in a sudden crisis.
陛下 请听我说 求您了
Majesty, please. Listen to me, I beg you!
城堡之下隧道挖成指日可待
We are only days away from mining under the castle…
看在上帝份上 求您网开一面
For the love of God, please.
无辜丧命之人已数不胜数
So many, many lives lost, and for what?
陛下 请您给我两天时间
Majesty, give me two days.
这是你的饭食吧
This is your food. Isn't it?
城里的人呢 他们吃什么
What about the people in the town? What are they eating?
有猫的就吃猫
Their cats. If they have cats.
大炮来啦
Cannons coming.
我们需要帮手
We need some help over here!
你为什么放了我父亲
Why did you let my father go?
我审问过他
I questioned him.
他对城中防御一无所知
He couldn't tell me anything useful about the town's defenses.
你以为我知道吗
And I can?
为何把我囚禁于此
Why are you keeping me here?
那些步枪准备好了吗
Are those muskets prepared?
玛丽女士
Lady Mary.
陛下 我翻译了伊拉兹马斯所著的
Your Majesty. I wanted to show.
《约翰福音》 请您过目
you my translation of Erasmus's "Gospel of St.John".
虽然刚刚开始
It is only started.
但这是献给您的
But it is dedicated to you…
因为我知道我们的信仰对您是多么重要
Since I know how much our faith matters to you.
多谢费心 玛丽女士
Thank you, Lady Mary.
我深受感动
I am deeply touched.
过来
Come!
能和你们三个在一起令我欣喜不已
This is so nice for me. To be with all three of you together…
一家人本该如此
Which I think is as it should be!
爱德华王子 请殿下注意言行
Prince Edward! Prince Edward! A little decorum, please!
- 爱德华 - 殿下 请过来
- Edward! - Come here, your Grace.
告诉我
Now, tell me,
你爱布莱恩女士 对吗
you love the Lady Bryan, don't you?
是的
Yes.
我想她也爱你
I think she loves you too.
但我想如今确是殿下该离开
But I think that it is time you were breeched.
布莱恩女士和奶妈的时候了
from the Lady Bryan and her nurses.
殿下年岁已足 是时候
and I think that you are old enough.
跟随导师学习了 殿下认为呢
to be placed with your tutors, don't you think?
我想是的
I suppose so.
殿下毋需担心 自然有其他男孩伴读
Well, don't worry. There'll be other boys too.
比如萨福克公爵的儿子亨利
There'll be the Duke of Suffolk's son Henry.
不仅局限于学习语言和圣经
And it won't be all learning languages.
还会学习网球和剑术
and scriptures. You'll also learn tennis and fencing,
音乐和舞蹈 会很有意思的 对吧
music and dance. Well, that will be fun, won't it?
晚安 王子殿下 谢谢你 布莱恩女士
Good night, Prince. Lady Bryan, thank you.
- 陛下晚安 - 晚安
- Good night, your Majesty. - Good night.
陛下
Your Majesty.
- 晚安 陛下 - 晚安 玛丽女士
- Good night, your Majesty. - Good night, Lady Mary.
来 小姑娘 让我抱抱你
Come here, young lady. Let me hug you.
我对你期望甚高 你一定不会令我失望
I expect great things of you, and I shall not be disappointed.
我一定尽力
I hope not.
宝贝 去睡吧
Now off to bed, sweet girl.
艾什莉小姐 请等一下
Mistress Ashley, a moment.
安 你过来
Anne.
我认为你值得信任
I believe that I can trust you.
我听说你家人都是改革者
I think that your family are reformers.
是的 陛下
Yes, Madam.
伊丽莎白女士的生母 安妮·博林
Lady Elizabeth's mother, Anne Boleyn,
也曾是路德教徒和改革者
was also a Lutheran and a reformer.
所以 我认为这是我的责任
I suppose it is my duty, therefore,
让她的女儿和母亲信仰一致
to bring the daughter up in the mother's faith.
爱什莉小姐 你对此有何异议
Would you have any objection to that, Mistress Ashley?
并无异议 陛下
None, your Majesty.
我很荣幸可以帮助公主
I should be proud to help the Princess.
承续其母亲的荣耀与慈辉 她的一生及信仰
thus honor the memory of her mother, whose life and whose faith…
如此崇重 怎能被轻易诋散
Too many so easily disparage.
好的 那么我将指派
Good. Then I will appoint.
罗杰·阿舍姆做她的导师 他也是我们的人
as her tutor Roger Ascham. He is also one of us.
爱什莉小姐 记住 此次谈话请务必保密
Mistress Ashley, this conversation never happened.
- 晚安 - 晚安 陛下
- Good night. - Good night, your Majesty.
晚安
Good night.
怎么
What?
我违背了自己的诺言
I broke my promise.
我逃跑了
I escaped.
但我又回来了
But I came back.
你的头还在渗血
You've got blood on your head.
开火 前进
Take shots. Come on! Forward!
前进 勇往直前
Forward! For your lives!
感谢你们
Thank you.
每一个人
All of you.
能与你们并肩奋战
It has been an honor and a privilege.
实感荣幸
to have worked alongside men such as you.
上帝与你同在
God be with you.
- 保重 - 上帝保佑
- Gratia. - God bless you, sir.
保重 米勒
Gratia Mille.
走吧
Go.
清开道路 清开道路
Clear the way! Clear the way!
快点 吉罗拉莫 快点
Come on Girolamo, come on.
走 快跑
Go! Run!
快跑
Run!
他欺骗了我 这个诳徒
He lied to me! He's a charlatan!
吉罗拉莫又犯傻了
Girolamo's mad again!
快 快跑
Go, go! Run!
不
No!
- 吉罗拉莫 - 别管我
- Girolamo! - Save yourself!
快过来 快过来
Get in here, get in here, get in here!
他们受伤了
They're injured in the mine!
这有人 快点 把他弄出来
We found somebody! Quickly, get him out!
继续 继续啊
Go on! Go on, sir!
英格兰万岁
England!
城墙塌了
The wall is down!
还有其他人吗
Is there anyone else?
还有别人吗
Are there any others?
- 还有其他人活着吗 - 没了
- Is there anyone else alive in there? - No.
万岁 英格兰
England!
队列指挥官 集合
Section Commanders, form up!
集合队伍 准备攻城
Form up your men! Prepare to take the city!
前进
Forward!
- 准备攻城 - 太棒了
- Prepare to take the city! - Yes.
孩子们 玛丽女士
Children! Lady Mary!
这是从法国传来的消息
There is great news from France!
国王已经攻克了布洛涅
The king has taken Boulogne.
他神勇无敌并大获全胜
He is safe and triumphant.
你的父王是个大英雄
Your father is a hero!
他夺回了布洛涅
He has captured Boulogne!
他很快便能凯旋了
I'm certain he'll be home very soon.
真是太棒了
How wonderful.
面对所向披靡的国王陛下
Most victorious Prince,
作为布洛涅的总督
as Governor of Boulogne,
我只能选择投降并交出城镇钥匙
I have no choice but to surrender the keys of the town.
有劳了
Monsieur.
我相信仁慈的陛下可以允许
I trust your Majesty will allow the inhabitants.
城内居民以及卸甲的兵丁
of the town and its unarmed garrison.
安然离去
to leave unmolested and in safety.
我以国王的名誉保证其安全
I do so swear, on my honor.
尽管你等愚众 曾弃神乱旨
Although you and your company, despite God's will.
逆天行事
and contrary to all justice,
强占应属本王继承的领土
withheld from me a town which, being a noble part.
英格兰的城池
of my inheritance, belonged to me.
恭贺陛下此番得胜
Well, I congratulate your Majesty.
全法国最为峻丽的城镇已归于您的麾下
You have captured one of the most beautiful towns in France.
弹尽粮绝之际 他们有人吃起了马肉
In their great necessity, many of them ate horseflesh.
看他们落荒而逃时 连牧师都饿得清秀了
Did you see them go out? Even the priests were thin!
说说看 赫福德大人…
So, my Lord Hertford…
此役得失究竟如何
Was it well done or not?
夺回属于我们的遗产和领土
Was it not God's will that we should reclaim.
是否顺应神意
part of our just rights and inheritance?
陛下 夺回布洛涅一役
Majesty, the capture of Boulogne.
必将永驻每位英国子民的心中
will live forever in the hearts of all Englishmen.
亨利八世 将成为我大英王族
And the eighth Henry as well as the fifth,
第五位彪炳史册的君主
in the glorious annals of our realm.
我视布洛涅为「掌上明珠」
I call Boulogne "Our daughter."
我便应是「布洛涅的太王圣父」
And I am the "King's Highness of Boulogne!"
- 我很期待 - 赫福德
- I look forward… - Hertford.
- 陛下 - 我在那还有很多未完成的生意
- Majesty. - I have a lot of unfinished business there.
- 诸位 干杯 - 干杯
- A toast! To all. - To all!
- 为胜利干杯 - 为胜利干杯
- And to victory. - And to victory!
陛下
Your Majesty.
阁下
Your Grace.
公爵大人 我要特别感谢你
Your Grace, I have much to thank you for.
此次战役中 你可谓战绩出众 功勋卓越
You have distinguished yourself above all in this campaign.
谢陛下隆恩
I am grateful to your Majesty.
臣忖度 接下来是否要进军巴黎
And now, I assume, we are march on Paris?
为何有如此想法
Why would you assume that?
陛下恕罪 臣愚钝
Forgive me, your Majesty. I don't understand.
臣窃以为与罗马帝国结盟正为此番
I thought that was the purpose of the pact with the Emperor.
在你看来
Do you suppose.
此刻正值寒冬 我军损兵折将
we should march on Paris with half an army,
病残累累 何以进攻巴黎
with thousands of sick soldiers, and in winter?
大人 非也
No, your Grace,
现在 布洛涅于我更重于巴黎
right now, Boulogne is now far more important to me than Paris…
岂止十倍
Than ten Parises!
就此打住 班师回朝
No, we shall back to England.
我军已夺得大捷
We have gained here a singular victory…
我已经心满意足
And I mean to hold onto it.
命萨里留守既可
I shall leave Surrey in command of the town.
- 萨里大人 - 正是
- Surrey? - Yes.
有何异议 公爵
Is that a problem, your Grace?
回陛下 没有
No, your Majesty.
大人
Your Grace.
（理查·雷兰）
对不起
I'm sorry.
你说的是这个
Is that what you want?
把那边的木头搬走
Move all that wood over there!
我可以走了吗
Am I free to go?
当然
Yes.
可以走了
You're free to go.
你不拿我换赎金了
You didn't ask for a ransom?
- 不 - 都给我站起来
- No. - Up on your feet.
你是不是觉得我一文不值
Then do you think I'm not worth anything?
你是我心中至宝
You are worth everything.
是否还要火药
Need some more powder?
- 跟我回去 - 回哪里
- Come back with me. - Where?
英格兰
To England.
- 给你当… - 是的长官 直走
- As your… - Yes sir, straight away, sir.
情妇 你的法国婊子
…mistress? Your French whore?
- 不是 - 那是什么
- No. - Then what?
我爱你
Je t'aime.
[拉丁语]我只想说 我爱你
Sólo quiero decir que te quiero.
夫人
My Lady.
陛下
Your Majesty,
得见陛下龙体康健
it makes me so glad.
臣妾喜不自胜
to see you so well and happy.
更能安全还朝 感谢上帝
And returned safe, thank God.
还有战事大捷 感谢上帝
And victorious, thank God!
还有战事大捷
And victorious.
凯特
Kate.
各位同僚 此般大肆宴席
Gentlemen, for all this celebration,
我却甚为担忧
I am very worried about our state of affairs.
国王大举征战 国库恐已告罄
The King's enterprise has bankrupted our exchequer.
理查德大人 我所言不虚吧
Is that not correct, Sir Richard?
我们已经无计可施
We are at our wit's end to know how to get revenues.
筹不到布洛涅战款
to pay for the Boulogne campaign,
甚至今后两三月的开支都无法承担
or even shift for the next two or three months.
近日 我国频频与法国和苏格兰开战
We are at war with France and with Scotland.
罗马主教对此恨之入骨
We have the enmity of the Bishop of Rome.
因此罗马帝国与我方盟约已裂
We no longer have assurances of friendship with the Emperor.
这场大战不得民心
This war has proved noisome to the realm.
并且致使民生凋敝
and disastrous for our merchants.
先生们 上帝助我们
Oh gentlemen, God help us,
如今的世道
we live in a world where.
知礼之古风不再
reason and learning no longer prevail.
盟约无信义可言
and covenants are little regarded.
更有甚者 当今王后竟然是异教徒
And where it seems even our Queen is a heretic.
所言极是
It's true.
如此大逆之人必遭天谴
And it will be God's work to destroy her.
- 大使大人 - 大人
- Your Excellency. - Excellency.
- Your Excellency. - Your Grace.
二位陛下
Your Majesties,
下臣此番前来告知
you should know that,
由于臣年老多病
due to my infirmity,
特提请告老还乡
I have applied for a recall to Spain.
此刻下臣正在等待罗马皇帝钦允
and even now I am awaiting the Emperor's permission.
夫人
Madam,
臣愿借此良机
I would like to take this opportunity to thank you,
代罗马皇帝陛下感谢您
on behalf of his Majesty the Emperor,
悉心抚育玛丽女士
for all that you have done for the Lady Mary.
以及为英西两国邦交友好竭尽心力
and for fostering the friendship between England and Spain.
大使大人 本宫对玛丽女士之情谊
Excellency, what I have done for the Lady Mary.
本不足一提
is much less than I would like to do,
更是职之所系
as well as being my duty in every respect.
而言及两国邦交友好
And as for the friendship between our two countries,
既是对两国不可或缺 大有裨益
I have done and will do nothing to prevent it.
本宫之前不予插手
from growing still further, as the friendship is.
今后更是不会
so necessary and both sovereigns…
阻挠
so good.
夫人 您所言极是
As are you, my Lady.
大使大人
Excellency!
陛下
Majesty.
寡人得知贵国国王和法王
I hear your Master has signed.
签署单方协议
a separate treaty with the French.
可有此事
Is it true?
我问你可有此事
I asked you if it was true!
难以启齿吗 尤斯塔斯
Is it so hard a question, Eustace?
回禀陛下 确有此事
Yes, it's true, your Majesty.
他为何如此
And why should he do that?
我们本是同盟
We were supposed to be allies.
陛下定然别无他选
I believe his Majesty had no choice.
卢森堡一役 我军久攻不下
He had spent too long besieging the town of Luxembourg;
将士疾病缠身 战力锐减
His army was riddled with disease.
那也不能做出此等勾当
He still should not have done it!
欺瞒寡人
Behind my back!
朕如此信任他
I trusted him…
- 他却背信弃义 - 陛下 我相信…
- And he betrayed me. - Your Majesty, I am sure…
别说了 你这辈子都在为他辩解
No, you defended and excused him your whole life!
他根本不值得信任
He is not to be trusted…
你也省省吧
And you should be relieved.
今后不必再殚精竭虑 满嘴谎言
that you no longer have to lie on his behalf.
朕赐你离开宫廷
You have my permission to leave my court.
早日卸甲归田 尽享天伦 退下吧
I wish you a long and happy retirement, your Excellency.
陛下 臣告退
Your Majesty.
- 大使阁下 - 再会 大使阁下
- Your Excellency. - Farewell, your Excellency.
上帝保佑 大使阁下
God speed, your Excellency.
她比我高吧
She is taller than me, isn't she?
略高一点
A little.
她是个怎样的人
How would you describe her?
她是我妻子
I would describe her as my wife.
我何时能见见她
When shall I meet her?
你想见她吗
Do you want to meet her?
不 只是想见见你儿子
No. But your son…
是亨利吧 有空想见见
Henry? Yes, sometime.
你在想什么
What are you thinking?
想我曾心如死水
That I was dead,
如今又枯木逢春
and am alive again.
让我看看你
Let me look at you.
说话啊
Say something.
尽在不言中
Words aren't important.
你不能走 我不许你走
You mustn't go. I forbid it.
女士 我别无选择
My Lady, I have to.
你很清楚我无能为力
You can see how it is with me.
那我怎么办
And what about me?
女士 让凯瑟琳王后照顾您
Madam, I don't think I could have ever left you.
再好不过了
in better care than Queen Catherine's.
我相信她爱你
I believe she loves you.
她也许爱我
She may love me.
我不清楚
I don't know.
我只知道她与我们信仰不同
What I do know is that she is not of our faith.
尽管她努力伪装 但毕竟不是天主教徒
She pretends… but she is not a Catholic.
- 她是异教徒 你还让她照顾我 - 女士
- She is a heretic- and still you leave me in her care! - Madam…
不
No…
这不是你的错
No, it is not your fault.
是我的错 如果我身为王子 而非女儿身
It is my fault. If I had been a boy and not a girl,
这一切就不会发生
none of this would have ever happened.
英格兰必会虔诚如昔
And England would still be faithful.
公主 我恳求你
Princess! I beg you.
我年岁见长 早非懵懂孩童
I am a lot older than I was when I first knew you.
也懂明察世事
And wiser.
我不知道将来能否结婚
I do not know if I shall ever be married,
能否登基为王
or if I will ever be Queen.
或许都不行 但若有朝一日成为女王
Probably neither. But if I do become Queen,
我现在愿以圣福音书
I swear to you now on the Holy Gospels.
和生母的灵魂发誓
and on the soul of my mother,
定要让英格兰虔诚向教 绝无二心
that I will make England faithful again.
我愿为此付出一切代价
I will do whatever it takes,
不管要烧死多少异教徒
I will burn however many heretics I have to,
哪怕血流成河 尸横遍野
I will spill as much blood as I have to,
也要让这不幸的国度重归天主教的怀抱
to make this unfortunate realm Catholic again,
医病疗伤 愿神助我
and heal it, so help me God.
告辞了
May I?
收下这枚戒指
Take this ring,
但求睹物思人
in memory of me.
这是罗马皇帝赐我的礼物
It was a gift from the Emperor…
是你母亲送给他的
Who received it from your mother.
启禀陛下
Your Majesty,
我们收到消息
we have received news that,
罗马皇帝不仅与法国
as well as concluding his separate peace treaty.
在克雷西握手言和
with the French at Crecy, the Emperor has.
还准许其女儿与
given permission for a marriage between his daughter.
奥尔良公爵成婚
and the Duke of Orleans.
知道了
All right.
不止这些
There is further news.
我们得知法国皇太子
We understand that the Dauphin,
率领三万六千人的大军
and an army of over 36, 000 men.
准备进军布洛涅
are preparing to march on Boulogne.
朕要欣赏普天同庆 举国欢腾的景象
I want my victory to be celebrated in every house in England.
此战之辉煌 必将万古传扬
It was, after all, a very glorious affair.
你去安排 要让每座教堂鸣钟致谢
I want you to arrange for every bell to be rung.
要让感恩的祷文响彻云霄
and a mass of Thanksgiving to be said in every church.
朕要布洛涅这个名字
I want the name "Boulogne"
铭刻在每个英国人心中
imprinted on every English heart…
一如「阿金库尔」
Just like "Agincourt"!
遵命 陛下
Yes, your Majesty.